Namaskar.
مرحباً.
I'm a movie star, I'm 51 years of age,
أنا نجم سينمائي، أبلغ من العمر 51 عاماً،
and I don't use Botox as yet.
ولم استخدم البوتكس حتى الآن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I'm clean, but I do behave like you saw like a 21-year-old in my movies.
لذا أنا نقي، ولكنني أتصرف كما رأيتم كشخص لديه 21 عاماً في أفلامي.
Yeah, I do that.
نعم، أنا أفعل ذلك.
I sell dreams, and I peddle love to millions of people back home in India
أنا أبيع الأحلام، وأنشر الحب للملايين من الناس في وطني الهند
who assume that I'm the best lover in the world.
الذين يفترضون أنني أفضل عاشق في العالم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If you don't tell anyone, I'm going to tell you I'm not,
إذا كنتم لن تخبروا أحداً، سأقول لكم أنني لست كذلك،
but I never let that assumption go away.
لكنني لن أترك هذا الافتراض يزول.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I've also been made to understand
لقد أفهموني أيضاً
there are lots of you here who haven't seen my work,
أن الكثير منكم هنا لم يشاهدوا أعمالي،
and I feel really sad for you.
وأنا أشعر حقاً بالحزن لأجلكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
That doesn't take away from the fact that I'm completely self-obsessed,
هذا لا ينفي حقيقة أنني مهووس تماماً بذاتي،
as a movie star should be.
كما ينبغي لنجم سينما أن يكون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's when my friends, Chris and Juliet called me here
عندما دعاني أصدقائي، كريس وجولييت إلي هنا
to speak about the future "you."
لأتحدث عن المستقبل "أنت".
Naturally, it follows I'm going to speak about the present me.
وبطبيعة الحال، ما سيحدث أنني سأتحدث عن الحاضر "أنا".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Because I truly believe that humanity is a lot like me.
لأنني أعتقد حقاً أن الإنسانية تشبهني.
It is. It is.
إنها كذلك، إنها كذلك
It's an aging movie star,
إنه نجم أفلام مسن،
grappling with all the newness around itself,
يتصارع مع جميع الحداثة من حوله،
wondering whether it got it right in the first place,
يتسائل ما اذا كان حصل عليها بطريقة صحيحة أولاً.
and still trying to find a way
ولا يزال يحاول أن يجد طريقة
to keep on shining regardless.
ليبقى مشرقاً رغم كل شئ.
I was born in a refugee colony in the capital city of India, New Delhi.
لقد ولدت في مستعمرة لللاجئين في العاصمة الهندية، نيودلهي.
And my father was a freedom fighter.
وكان والدي مناضلاً من أجل الحرية.
My mother was, well, just a fighter like mothers are.
وكانت والدتي، مقاتلة فحسب مثلما تكون الأمهات.
And much like the original homo sapiens,
وكما هو حال الكائن البشري البدائي،
we struggled to survive.
كنا نناضل من أجل البقاء.
When I was in my early 20s,
عندما كنت في أوائل العشرينات،
I lost both my parents,
فقدت كلا والدي،
which I must admit seems a bit careless of me now,
الذي لابد أن أعترف أنه جعلني طائشاً في الوقت الحالي.
but --
لكن --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I do remember the night my father died,
أتذكر الليلة التي مات فيها والدي،
and I remember the driver of a neighbor who was driving us to the hospital.
وأتذكر جارنا السائق الذي كان يقودنا إلى المستشفى.
He mumbled something about "dead people don't tip so well"
تمتم شيئاً عن أن "الميتون لا يدفعون بقشيشاً جيداً."
and walked away into the dark.
ومشى بعيداً في الظلام.
And I was only 14 then,
كان عمري آنذاك 14عاماً فقط،
and I put my father's dead body in the back seat of the car,
وضعت جثة والدي في المقعد الخلفي للسيارة،
and my mother besides me,
وأمي إلى جانبي،
I started driving back from the hospital to the house.
ثم بدأت بالقيادة من المستشفى إلى المنزل.
And in the middle of her quiet crying, my mother looked at me and she said,
وفي وسط بكائها الخافت، نظرت أمي في وجهي وقالت:
"Son, when did you learn to drive?"
"بني، متى تعلمت القيادة؟"
And I thought about it and realized, and I said to my mom,
وفكرت في ذلك وأدركت، وقلت لوالدتي،
"Just now, Mom."
"للتو، أمي".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So from that night onwards,
لذا منذ تلك الليلة فصاعداً،
much akin to humanity in its adolescence,
أقرب إلى الإنسانية في مرحلة مراهقتها،
I learned the crude tools of survival.
تعلمت الأدوات البدائية للبقاء على قيد الحياة.
And the framework of life was very, very simple then, to be honest.
وكان إطار الحياة بسيطاً للغاية حينها، لأكون صادقاً.
You know, you just ate what you got
كما تعلمون، أنت فقط تأكل ما تحصل عليه
and did whatever you were told to do.
وتفعل كل ما عليك القيام به.
I thought celiac was a vegetable,
كنت أعتقد أن الاضطرابات الهضمية كانت نباتاً.
and vegan, of course, was Mr. Spock's lost comrade in "Star Trek."
وأن النباتي، هو بالطبع، كان رفيق السيد سبوك المفقود في فيلم "حرب النجوم".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You married the first girl that you dated,
تتزوج أول فتاة تواعدها،
and you were a techie if you could fix the carburetor in your car.
وتكون فنياً إذا كنت تستطيع إصلاح المكربن في سيارتك.
I really thought that gay was a sophisticated English word for happy.
كنت أعتقد حقًا أن مثلي هي كلمة إنجليزية راقية للسعادة.
And Lesbian, of course, was the capital of Portugal, as you all know.
وسحاقية، بالطبع، كانت عاصمة البرتغال، كما تعلمون جميعًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Where was I?
أين كنت؟
We relied on systems
لقد اعتمدنا على الأنظمة
created through the toil and sacrifice of generations before
التي خلقت من خلال تعب وتضحيات الأجيال السابقة
to protect us,
لحمياتنا،
and we felt that governments actually worked for our betterment.
وشعرنا أن الحكومات عملت فعلاً لخدمتنا.
Science was simple and logical,
كان العلم بسيطاً ومنطقياً،
Apple was still then just a fruit
كانت التفاحة لا تزال مجرد فاكهة
owned by Eve first and then Newton,
ملكتها حواء أولاً ثم نيوتن،
not by Steve Jobs, until then.
وليس ستيف جوبز، في ذلك الحين.
And "Eureka!" was what you screamed
و"وجدتها!" هو ما تصرخ به
when you wanted to run naked on the streets.
إذا أردت الجري عارياً في الشوارع.
You went wherever life took you for work,
تذهب أينما تأخذك الحياة للعمل،
and people were mostly welcoming of you.
وكان الناس في الغالب يرحبون بك.
Migration was a term then
وكانت الهجرة لا تزال حينها مصطلحاً
still reserved for Siberian cranes, not human beings.
محجوزاً لطيور الكركي السيبيرية، وليس للبشر.
Most importantly, you were who you were
الأهم من ذلك، تكون كما أنت
and you said what you thought.
وتقول ما تعتقد.
Then in my late 20s,
ثم في أواخر العشرينات،
I shifted to the sprawling metropolis of Mumbai,
انتقلت إلى الأطراف المترامية لمدينة مومباي،
and my framework,
وإطاري الخاص،
like the newly industrialized aspirational humanity,
كالبشرية الطموحة حديثة الصنع،
began to alter.
بدأ يتغير.
In the urban rush for a new, more embellished survival,
في الاندفاع الحضاري من أجل الحداثة، والبقاء بشكل منمق،
things started to look a little different.
بدأت الأمور تبدو مختلفة قليلاً.
I met people who had descended from all over the world,
قابلت أناساً ينحدرون من كل أنحاء العالم،
faces, races, genders, money-lenders.
شخصيات بارزة، أعراق، أجناس، مرابين.
Definitions became more and more fluid.
أصبحت التعاريف أكثر وأكثر مرونة.
Work began to define you at that time
بدأ العمل في تعريفك في ذلك الوقت
in an overwhelmingly equalizing manner,
بطريقة عادلة بالإجماع،
and all the systems started to feel less reliable to me,
وجميع الأنظمة بدأت تبدو أقل موثوقية بالنسبة لي
almost too thick to hold on
تقريبا خانقةً جداً للاستمرار
to the diversity of mankind
في تنوع الجنس البشري
and the human need to progress and grow.
والحاجة الإنسانية للتقدم والنمو.
Ideas were flowing with more freedom and speed.
كانت الأفكار تتدفق مع المزيد من الحرية والسرعة.
And I experienced the miracle of human innovation and cooperation,
وشهدت معجزة الابتكار والتعاون المشترك،
and my own creativity,
وإبداعي الخاص،
when supported by the resourcefulness of this collective endeavor,
عندما دعمه دهاء تلك المساعي الجماعية،
catapulted me into superstardom.
قاذفةً بي إلى النجومية.
I started to feel that I had arrived,
بدأت أشعر بأنني قد وصلت،
and generally, by the time I was 40, I was really, really flying.
وعموماً، بحلول الوقت الذي بلغت فيه 40 عاماً، كنت أحلق حقاً.
I was all over the place.
لقد كنت في كل مكان.
You know? I'd done 50 films by then
تعلمون؟ كنت قد أديت 50 فيلماً في ذلك الوقت
and 200 songs,
و200 أغنية،
and I'd been knighted by the Malaysians.
وكنت قد مُنحت وساماً من قبل الماليزيين.
I had been given the highest civil honor by the French government,
لقد منحت أعلى وسام شرف مدني من قبل الحكومة الفرنسية،
the title of which for the life of me I can't pronounce even until now.
و الذي لم أتمكن على الإطلاق من نطق اسمه حتى الآن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm sorry, France, and thank you, France, for doing that.
أنا آسف، فرنسا، وشكراً لكم، فرنسا، للقيام بذلك.
But much bigger than that, I got to meet Angelina Jolie --
ولكن الأكبر من ذلك بكثير، لقد التقيت أنجلينا جولي -
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
for two and a half seconds.
لمدة ثانيتين ونصف.
And I'm sure she also remembers that encounter somewhere.
وأنا متأكد من أنها تتذكر أيضاً ذلك اللقاء.
OK, maybe not.
حسنا، ربما لا.
And I sat next to Hannah Montana on a round dinner table
وجلست بجوار هانا مونتانا على طاولة عشاء مستديرة
with her back towards me most of the time.
مع ظهرها نحوي معظم الوقت.
Like I said, I was flying, from Miley to Jolie,
مثلما قلت، كنت أحلق، من مايلي إلى جولي،
and humanity was soaring with me.
وكانت الإنسانية ترتفع معي.
We were both pretty much flying off the handle, actually.
كنا إلى حد كبير نحلق بعيداً عن السرب في الحقيقة.
And then you all know what happened.
ثم أنتم تعرفون ما حدث.
The internet happened.
جاء عصر الإنترنت.
I was in my late 40s,
كنت في أواخر الأربعينات،
and I started tweeting like a canary in a birdcage
وبدأت بالتغريد كطائر كناري في قفص العصافير
and assuming that, you know, people who peered into my world
وأفترض أنه، كما تعلمون، الناس الذين اتحدوا في عالمي
would admire it
سوف يقدرونه
for the miracle I believed it to be.
لمعجزة ما، أعتقد أن هذا سوف يكون
But something else awaited me and humanity.
ولكن شيئاً آخر كان في انتظاري انا والبشرية.
You know, we had expected an expansion of ideas and dreams
كما تعلمون، كنا نتوقع توسعاً في الأفكار والأحلام
with the enhanced connectivity of the world.
مع تعزيز الاتصال بالعالم.
We had not bargained for the village-like enclosure of thought,
لم نكن نتوقع أن يكون هناك تطويق للفكر،
of judgment, of definition
للحكم، للتعريف
that flowed from the same place
الذي تدفق من نفس المكان
that freedom and revolution was taking place in.
الذي يناشد بالحرية والثورة.
Everything I said took a new meaning.
كل شيء أقوله كان يأخذ معنى جديداً.
Everything I did -- good, bad, ugly --
كل ما فعلته -- جيد، سيئ، قبيح --
was there for the world to comment upon and judge.
كان هناك ليعلق عليه العالم ويصدر الأحكام.
As a matter of fact, everything I didn't say or do also
في الواقع، كل شيء لم أقله أو أفعله أيضاً
met with the same fate.
لاقى نفس المصير.
Four years ago,
منذ أربع سنوات،
my lovely wife Gauri and me decided to have a third child.
قررت أنا وزوجتي الجميلة غوري أن ننجب طفلاً ثالثاً.
It was claimed on the net
تم الادعاء على الإنترنت
that he was the love child
أنه كان طفلاً غير شرعياً
of our first child
لطفلنا البكر
who was 15 years old.
الذي كان يبلغ 15 عاماً.
Apparently, he had sown his wild oats with a girl
على ما يبدو، انه أقام علاقة جنسية مع فتاة
while driving her car in Romania.
أثناء قيادته سيارتها في رومانيا.
And yeah, there was a fake video to go with it.
و نعم، كان هناك فيديو مزيف يتماشى مع ذلك.
And we were so disturbed as a family.
وكنا نشعر بالانزعاج الشديد كعائلة
My son, who is 19 now,
ابني، في سن الـ 19 الآن،
even now when you say "hello" to him,
حتى الآن عندما أقول له "مرحباً"،
he just turns around and says,
انه يستدير فقط ويقول:
"But bro, I didn't even have a European driving license."
"ولكن يا أخي، لم أكن أملك حتى رخصة قيادة أوروبية ".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah.
أجل.
In this new world,
في هذا العالم الجديد،
slowly, reality became virtual and virtual became real,
ببطء، أصبح الواقع افتراضياً وأصبح الافتراضي واقعياً،
and I started to feel
وبدأت أشعر
that I could not be who I wanted to be or say what I actually thought,
أني لا أستطيع أن أكون الذي أردت أن أكون أو أقول ما فكرت به فعلاً،
and humanity at this time
والإنسانية في هذا الوقت
completely identified with me.
متطابقة تماماً معي.
I think both of us were going through our midlife crisis,
أعتقد أن كلانا كان يمر بأزمة منتصف العمر،
and humanity, like me, was becoming an overexposed prima donna.
والإنسانية، مثلي، تعرضت لاضطراب مفرط.
I started to sell everything,
بدأت في بيع كل شيء،
from hair oil to diesel generators.
من زيت الشعر حتى مولدات الديزل.
Humanity was buying everything
الإنسانية كانت تشتري كل شيء
from crude oil to nuclear reactors.
من النفط الخام إلى المفاعلات النووية.
You know, I even tried to get into a skintight superhero suit
كما تعلمون، حتى حاولت الدخول في بدلة الرجل الخارق الضيقة
to reinvent myself.
لإعادة اكتشاف نفسي.
I must admit I failed miserably.
يجب أن أعترف أنني فشلت فشلاً ذريعاً.
And just an aside I want to say on behalf of all the Batmen, Spider-Men
وبالمناسبة نيابة عن كل من الرجل الوطواط، الرجل العنكبوت
and Supermen of the world,
ورجال العالم الخارقين،
you have to commend them,
عليكم أن تثنوا عليهم جميعاً،
because it really hurts in the crotch, that superhero suit.
لأن بدلة الخارقين هذه، تؤلم حقاً بين الساقين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, I'm being honest. I need to tell you this here.
نعم، أنا اتكلم جدياً. أريد أن أخبركم هذا هنا.
Really.
حقاً.
And accidentally, I happened to even invent a new dance form
و عن طريق الصدفة، لقد حدث حتى أنني ابتكرت نموذج رقص جديد
which I didn't realize, and it became a rage.
الذي لم أدرك أنه أصبح صرعة ،
So if it's all right,
لذا إن كان لا بأس في ذلك،
and you've seen a bit of me, so I'm quite shameless, I'll show you.
وقد رأيتم جانباً مني، لذا بلا خجل سأريكم.
It was called the Lungi dance.
إنها تدعى رقصة اللونجي
So if it's all right, I'll just show you. I'm talented otherwise.
لذا إن لم يكن هناك مشكلة، سأريكم فحسب. انا موهوب بصورة مختلفة.
(Cheers)
(هتاف)
So it went something like this.
إذا هي شئ من هذا القبيل
Lungi dance. Lungi dance.
رقصة لونغي، رقصة لونغي.
Lungi dance. Lungi.
رقصة لونغي، لونغي.
That's it. It became a rage.
تلك هي، وأصبحت صرعة.
(Cheers)
(هتاف)
It really did.
حدث ذلك فعلاً.
Like you notice, nobody could make any sense of what was happening except me,
كما لاحظتم، لا يجد أحد منطقاً فيما كان يحدث إلا أنا،
and I didn't give a damn, really,
وأنا لم أكترث مطلقاً، حقاً،
because the whole world, and whole humanity,
لأن العالم بأسره، والإنسانية بكاملها،
seemed as confused and lost as I was.
بدت مرتبكة وضائعة مثلي تماماً.
I didn't give up then.
لم أستسلم حينها.
I even tried to reconstruct my identity on the social media
حتى أني حاولت إعادة بناء هويتي على وسائل الاعلام الاجتماعية
like everyone else does.
مثلما يفعل الآخرون.
I thought if I put on philosophical tweets out there
اعتقدت أني لو وضعت تغريدات فلسفية هناك
people will think I'm with it,
سوف يعتقد الناس أنني مع ذلك،
but some of the responses I got from those tweets
ولكن بعض الردود على هذه التغريدات
were extremely confusing acronyms which I didn't understand. You know?
كانت اختصارات محيرة للغاية لم افهمها. أتعلمون؟
ROFL, LOL.
مثل ROFL و LOL
"Adidas," somebody wrote back to one of my more thought-provoking tweets
كتب شخص ما Adidas تعليقاً على إحدى تغريداتي الأكثر إثارة للتفكير
and I was wondering why would you name a sneaker,
و كنت أتساءل لماذا ذكر اسم حذاء رياضي،
I mean, why would you write back the name of a sneaker to me?
أعني، لماذا علق باسم حذاء رياضي؟
And I asked my 16-year-old daughter, and she enlightened me.
وسألت ابنتي البالغة من العمر 16 عاماً، والتي قامت بتثقيفي.
"Adidas" now means "All day I dream about sex."
كلمة Adidas الآن اختصار "أنا أحلم طوال اليوم بالجنس".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Really.
حقاً.
I didn't know if you know that.
لا أعلم إذا كنتم تعرفون ذلك.
So I wrote back, "WTF" in bold to Mr. Adidas,
لذلك كتبت "اللعنة" للسيد أديداس،
thanking secretly that some acronyms and things won't change at all.
وشاكرا الله في سري أن بعض الاختصارات والأشياء لن تتغيرعلى الإطلاق.
WTF.
اللعنة.
But here we are.
ولكن ها نحن هنا.
I am 51 years old, like I told you,
عمري51 عاماً، كما أخبرتكم،
and mind-numbing acronyms notwithstanding,
وعلى الرغم من الاختصارات المتطرفة للغاية،
I just want to tell you
أريد أن أخبركم فحسب
if there has been a momentous time for humanity to exist,
إذا ما كان هناك وقت بالغ الأهمية لنجاة البشرية،
it is now,
فهو الآن،
because the present you is brave.
لأن الحاضر "أنت" هو الشجاعة.
The present you is hopeful.
الحاضر "أنت" هو الأمل.
The present you is innovative and resourceful,
الحاضر"أنت" هو الابتكار وسعة الحيلة،
and of course, the present you is annoyingly indefinable.
وبالطبع، الحاضر "أنت" لا يمكن تحديده بشكل مزعج.
And in this spell-binding,
وفي هذه اللحظات الفاتنة
imperfect moment of existence,
غير التامة في الوجود،
feeling a little brave just before I came here,
والشعور بقليل من الشجاعة قبل مجيئي هنا،
I decided to take a good, hard look at my face.
قررت أن اتخذ مظهراً جيداً وحاداً على وجهي.
And I realized that I'm beginning to look more and more
وأدركت أنني بدأت أشبه أكثر وأكثر
like the wax statue of me at Madame Tussaud's.
تمثالي الشمعي في متحف مدام توسود.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, and in that moment of realization,
نعم، وفي لحظة الإدراك تلك،
I asked the most central and pertinent question to humanity and me:
طرحت على نفسي والإنسانية أكثر سؤال محوري ووثيق الصلة:
Do I need to fix my face?
هل أحتاج إلى إصلاح وجهي؟
Really. I'm an actor, like I told you,
حقاً. أنا ممثل، كما أخبرتكم،
a modern expression of human creativity.
التعبير الحديث عن الإبداع البشري.
The land I come from
الأرض التي جئت منها
is the source of inexplicable but very simple spirituality.
هي مصدر الروحانية البسيطة رغم صعوبة تفسيرها،
In its immense generosity,
بسخائها الكبير،
India decided somehow
قررت الهند بطريقة أو بأخرى
that I, the Muslim son of a broke freedom fighter
أنني أنا، الإبن المسلم لمقاتل مفلس من أجل الحرية
who accidentally ventured into the business of selling dreams,
والذي خاطر مصادفة في تجارة بيع الأحلام،
should become its king of romance,
يجب أن يصبح ملكها في الرومانسية،
the "Badhshah of Bollywood,"
"ملك بوليوود"
the greatest lover the country has ever seen ...
أعظم عاشق رأته البلاد على الإطلاق ...
with this face.
بهذا الوجه.
Yeah.
نعم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Which has alternately been described as ugly, unconventional,
الذي بالتناوب وصف بالقبيح، الغير تقليدي،
and strangely, not chocolatey enough.
الغريب، والغير شيكولاتي بما فيه الكفاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The people of this ancient land
شعب هذه الأرض القديمة
embraced me in their limitless love,
احتضنني بحبه غير المحدود،
and I've learned from these people
ولقد تعلمت من هؤلاء الناس
that neither power nor poverty
أنه لا السلطة ولا الفقر
can make your life more magical
يمكن أن تجعل حياتك أكثر سحراً
or less tortuous.
أو أقل تعقيداً.
I've learned from the people of my country
لقد تعلمت من شعب بلدي
that the dignity of a life,
أن كرامة الحياة،
a human being, a culture, a religion, a country
الإنسان، الثقافة، الدين، الدولة
actually resides in its ability
يكمن في الواقع في قدرتها
for grace and compassion.
على الرحمة والتسامح.
I've learned that whatever moves you,
لقد تعلمت أنه أيا ً كان ما يحركك،
whatever urges you to create, to build,
أيا ً كان ما يدفعك للإبداع، للبناء،
whatever keeps you from failing,
مهما كان ما يحميك من الفشل
whatever helps you survive,
مهما كان ما يساعدك على البقاء،
is perhaps the oldest and the simplest emotion known to mankind,
ربما يكون لأقدم وأبسط عاطفة معروفة لدى البشر،
and that is love.
وذلك هو الحب.
A mystic poet from my land famously wrote,
لقد كتب شاعر صوفي من أرضي كتابة شهيرة،
(Recites poem in Hindi)
(يقرأ قصيدة باللغة الهندية)
(Poem ends)
(نهاية القصيدة)
Which loosely translates into that whatever --
والتي تترجم على نحو حر أيا يكن --
yeah, if you know Hindi, please clap, yeah.
نعم، إذا كنتم تعرفون الهندية، أرجو منكم التصفيق،
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's very difficult to remember.
فمن الصعب جدًا تذكرها.
Which loosely translates into actually saying
والتي يمكن ترجمتها حرفياً إلى
that all the books of knowledge that you might read
أن جميع كتب المعرفة التي ربما قرأتها
and then go ahead and impart your knowledge
ومن ثم مضيت قدماً ونقلت المعرفة الخاصة بك
through innovation, through creativity, through technology,
من خلال الابتكار، من خلال الإبداع من خلال التقنية،
but mankind will never be the wiser about its future
ولكن البشرية لن تكون أبداً أكثر حكمة حول مستقبلها
unless it is coupled with a sense of love and compassion for their fellow beings.
ما لم يقترن ذلك مع عاطفة الحب والرحمة لأبناء جنسها.
The two and a half alphabets which form the word "प्रेम,"
الحروف الهجائية التي تشكل كلمة Prem
which means "love,"
والتي تعني "الحب"
if you are able to understand that
إذا كنت قادراً على فهمها
and practice it,
وممارستها،
that itself is enough to enlighten mankind.
هذا بحد ذاته يكفي لتنوير البشرية.
So I truly believe the future "you"
لذلك أنا حقاً أعتقد أن المستقبل "أنت"
has to be a you that loves.
يجب أن يكون "أنت" من يحب.
Otherwise it will cease to flourish.
وإلا فإن الأمر سوف يتوقف عن الازدهار.
It will perish in its own self-absorption.
سوف تفنى في امتصاص نفسها.
So you may use your power
لذا يمكنك استخدام قوتك
to build walls
لبناء الجدران
and keep people outside,
وإبقاء الناس في الخارج،
or you may use it to break barriers and welcome them in.
أو يمكنك استخدامها لكسر الحواجز والترحيب بهم.
You may use your faith
يمكنك استخدام إيمانك
to make people afraid
لجعل الناس خائفين
and terrify them into submission,
وترهبهم لحملهم على الخضوع،
or you can use it to give courage to people
أو يمكنك استخدامه لإعطاء الشجاعة للناس
so they rise to the greatest heights of enlightenment.
حتى يرتقوا إلى أقصى آفاق التنوير.
You can use your energy
يمكنك استخدام طاقتك
to build nuclear bombs and spread the darkness of destruction,
لبناء القنابل النووية ونشر ظلام الدمار،
or you can use it to spread the joy of light to millions.
أو يمكنك استخدامه لنشر فرحة الإضاءة للملايين.
You may filthy up the oceans callously and cut down all the forests.
يمكنك أن تلوث المحيطات بقسوة، وتقطع جميع الغابات.
You can destroy the ecology,
يمكنك تدمير البيئة،
or turn to them with love
أو تتوجه إليها بالحب
and regenerate life from the waters and trees.
وتعيد صناعة الحياة من المياه والأشجار.
You may land on Mars
يمكنك أن تهبط على سطح المريخ
and build armed citadels,
وتبني القلاع المسلحة،
or you may look for life-forms and species to learn from and respect.
أو يمكنك البحث عن أشكال وأنواع من الحياة للتعلم منها وتعظيمها.
And you can use all the moneys we all have earned
يمكنك استخدام كل الأموال التي حصلنا عليها جميعاً
to wage futile wars
لشن حروب غير مجدية
and give guns in the hands of little children
ووضع البنادق في أيدي الأطفال الصغار
to kill each other with,
لقتل بعضهم البعض بها،
or you can use it
أو يمكنك استخدامه
to make more food
لتوفير المزيد من الطعام
to fill their stomachs with.
لملء بطونهم بها.
My country has taught me
لقد علمتني بلدي
the capacity for a human being to love is akin to godliness.
أن قدرة الإنسان على الحب هي أقرب للتقوى.
It shines forth in a world
إنه يضيء العالم
which civilization, I think, already has tampered too much with.
الذي أعتقد أن الحضارة قد عبثت به كثيراً.
In the last few days, the talks here, the wonderful people
في الأيام القليلة الماضية، المحادثات هنا، الناس الرائعون
coming and showing their talent,
الذين أتوا وعرضوا مواهبهم،
talking about individual achievements, the innovation, the technology,
متحدثين عن الإنجازات الفردية الابتكار، التقنية،
the sciences, the knowledge we are gaining by being here
والعلوم، المعرفة التي نكتسبها من خلال تواجدنا هنا
in the presence of TED Talks and all of you
في حضور محاضرات TED وأنتم جميعاً
are reasons enough for us to celebrate the future "us."
هي أسباب كافية بالنسبة لنا للاحتفال بالمستقبل "نحن".
But within that celebration
ولكن ضمن هذا الإحتفال
the quest to cultivate our capacity for love and compassion
السعي لتنمية قدرتنا على الحب والرحمة
has to assert itself,
ينبغي أن يفرض ذاته
just as equally.
تماماً بنفس القدر.
So I believe the future "you"
لذلك أعتقد أن المستقبل "أنت"
is an infinite you.
هو أنت غير المحدود.
It's called a chakra in India, like a circle.
إنها تسمى Chakra في الهند، مثل الدائرة.
It ends where it begins from to complete itself.
فهي تنتهي من حيث بدأت لاستكمال نفسها.
A you that perceives time and space differently
أنت الذي يدرك الزمان والمكان بشكل مختلف
understands both
يفهم كلاهما
your unimaginable
ما لا يمكن تصوره
and fantastic importance
من شأنك الرائع
and your complete unimportance in the larger context of the universe.
وعدم قدرتك الكاملة في السياق الأوسع للكون.
A you that returns back
" أنت" الذي ستسترد مجددًا
to the original innocence of humanity,
البراءة الأصلية للإنسانية،
which loves from the purity of heart,
الذي يحب من قلب نقي،
which sees from the eyes of truth,
الذي يرى بعيون الحقيقة،
which dreams from the clarity of an untampered mind.
الذي يحلم بعقل واضح غيرعابث.
The future "you" has to be
المستقبل "أنت" ينبغي أن يكون
like an aging movie star
مثل نجم سينمائي مسن
who has been made to believe that there is a possibility
الذي صنع اعتقاداً بأن هناك إمكانية
of a world which is completely,
لوجود عالم، والذي هو تماماً،
wholly, self-obsessively
كلياً، واقع بهوس
in love with itself.
في حب ذاته.
A world -- really, it has to be a you
حقاً، لابد أن يكون " أنت"
to create a world
لخلق العالم
which is its own best lover.
الذي يعد معشوقه الأفضل.
That I believe, ladies and gentlemen,
هذا ما أؤمن به، سيداتي سادتي،
should be the future "you."
ينبغي أن يكون المتسقبل " أنت".
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلاً لكم.
Shukriya.
أشكركم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً.